a useful feature within word
is the ability to merge the contents of
a letter
with the database of clients names and
addresses
in this example i'm going to use the
files that you can download from the
vision alone website
to show how you can link the names and
addresses of four clients
to the letter which can then be sent out
without having to type out each
individual person's names and addresses
so the first thing i need to do is open
the letter which i have done on the
screen there
and to access the mail merge tool i need
to go to the mailings tab so if i click
on the mailings tab
this brings up a range of options and
the tool we're going to use here is the
mail merge wizard so if i click on the
start meal merge
and select the step-by-step mail merge
wizard
that will then bring up the dialog box
on the right hand side
now there are six steps in the mail
merge process and we'll work through
each one individually
so the first one is select document type
so what type of document are you working
on well we're working on a letter
so we're happy with that and step two
and select the starting document so how
do you want to set up your letters
and again we're going to use the first
option here is use the current document
you could go from a template and start
from an existing document that's
somewhere else
so we'll now move to step three now at
this point this is where you're going to
link the letter
with the data source so what you need to
do is you need to browse
to the location where you see if the
spreadsheet containing the names and
addresses
downloaded so i'll save these and my
documents folder
in the it course and in the word
processing folder
and you will see this as an excel
spreadsheet and it is sample
mail merge addresses so i just simply
double click on that
and that then gives me the option so
it's asking me to select a table
and i'm happy with that i click ok
this then brings up the mail merge
recipients dialog box so this tells me
what the contents of the spreadsheet are
so i know there are four people within
that spreadsheet and the names and
addresses are all there
if i didn't want to send the letter to a
specific person i can
tick or untick that box and it will
remove them it won't include them
in the merge and when i'm happy with
that i click ok
and it is now time to move on to the
next step
so if i go to step four
this is about right your letter so if
you hadn't already done so at this point
you would write the letter
but what we need to do now is the letter
is already written so we simply need to
insert the address block and the
greeting line
so the address block is traditionally
inserted at the top left-hand section of
the letter
so i will place the cursor there where i
want the address block to appear
and if i look along to the right if i
click on address block
i then have the insert address block
dialog box
in here it will show me what the
addresses will look like
there are four recipients on the off so
it will then preview
each one and i'm happy with that so i
can then
select okay so it will insert the
address block
merge field i'm also going to add the
greeting line
and the greeting line would be just
above the main body of text so i'll
place the cursor there and select
reading line
again this will give me a dialog box
which shows me a demonstration of a
preview
of what will be seen on the letter
if i'm happy with that i click ok and
that inserts it reading
so now what we need to do is we need to
preview the letters
so i click on step five
you can see that the address block and
the greeting line have changed and
are now the full names and addresses of
the people
again i can preview each of the letters
to see that i'm happy with it
i can't exclude recipients or i can even
edit the recipient list at this point
so the final step would be to complete
the merge and if i selected print
i can then select all and i could print
out the letters